Previously on Gotham...
We will create a
legacy in this city.
Gotham falls... we rise.
Together.
Why don't you understand?
(grunts) You need me!
I'm the answer to
your life's question!
All this happened because of me,
because people
were trying to hurt me
and the people I care about.
CHANG: With reunification
underway and the bridges being rebuilt,
it is my honor to bestow
upon Captain James Gordon
the title of commissioner.
What do you mean you're leaving?
- Gotham's in good hands.
- Thank you, Bruce.
That you are the only
son that I will ever have.
And I could not be more proud.
(ship horn blowing)
(indistinct chatter)
BRUCE: Alfred...
I'm writing to let
you know I'm okay...
and that you won't hear
from me for some time.
But I will return...
when I know I'm able to
protect the people I love.
When Gotham needs me...
I will return.
♪♪♪♪
(sirens wailing in distance)
GORDON: It began
a few weeks ago.
Someone attacking
the gangs downtown.
No deaths so far, at least.
Hoods couldn't give
a description, but, uh,
they did mention a growling.
A growling?
It's a rumor; ignore it.
Oswald Cobblepot gets
out of Blackgate tomorrow.
One theory is he's
sending someone
to put the fear of God
into the underworld.
And you choose this moment
to hand in your resignation.
I told you that months ago.
That's not the point.
Look, things are
unstable. I-Isn't there, uh,
uh, some break-in
at a government warehouse
that you guys haven't solved yet?
Yeah, 'cause the
Feds won't tell us squat.
I'm not looking for excuses!
Look... you mean
something to this city.
You can't quit.
Not now.
Because of Wayne Tower.
Bruce Wayne is returning
home for the first time
in a decade for its opening.
The new Wayne Tower
represents hope for Gotham.
So, yeah... I need you.
Mayor James... I
told you I would stay
until after the Wayne inaugural.
Then I'm done.
If you'll excuse me,
I have a fund-raiser I
have to get ready for.
Good day, gentlemen.
BULLOCK: Jim.
I've had ten years, Harv.
It's time for someone
else to have a chance.
And you wait for Bruce to
come back to hang it up?
That's a coincidence?
I'm late. I have
to meet Barbara.
Yeah.
The queen of Gotham.
Tell me something.
Why didn't I buy up half
of Gotham on the cheap
after reunification?
Become a tycoon. Hmm?
Give a kiss to the little
one from Uncle Harv.
Will do.
(door opens)
GORDON: Hey, slugger.
Daddy!
(speaking indistinctly)
- Just do it.
- Yes, ma'am.
Hi, sweetheart.
So... did you hear from Bruce?
No.
Ten years and not a word.
But I'm assuming he'll be at the
gala for Wayne Tower tomorrow.
I want to see the look
on his face when I tell him,
in three months he won't
have the tallest building
in Gotham anymore.
Hmm.
Think he'll recognize you
with that caterpillar
on your top lip?
(chuckles)
Okay, munchkin,
I love you. (kisses)
Don't let her stay up too late.
Ice cream?
Yeah.
(lock buzzes, latch clicks)
(indistinct chatter)
Bruce is back.
(chuckles)
Big deal.
I knew him.
Back in the day.
Saved Gotham together.
(gasps) Oswald's being freed?
Hey!
I've been in here ten years!
Ten years!
I deserve to read the
newspaper, you mouth breather!
(chuckles)
Hey! Hey!
Hey!
Do you know who that is?
Jeremiah Valeska.
And yeah...
he's been a
vegetable for a decade.
Can't think. Can't feel.
But he is
a legend.
And if you're gonna
screw with a legend...
do it properly. (chuckling)
This never gets old. (chuckles)
(alarm ringing)
(inmates screaming)
Hey, buddy, I got
something for you.
Hey!
What are you doing?
Where are you taking me?
Come on.
NURSE: Out of the way.
Whoa.
Yup. It was time to admit it.
I was trying
something. It didn't work.
You liked it, right?
Totally.
At least now Bruce
will recognize you.
Hmm. That's very funny.
I wonder how much he's changed.
Well, it's been ten
years. I'd imagine a lot.
Well, we haven't.
I'm still a doctor.
You're still a cop.
Mm. Not for long.
Are you having second
thoughts about leaving?
Well...
I'm all for it.
But I know how much
this job means to you.
And how much the city
looks to you. It always has.
Well, that's just it.
I was hoping Gotham
would outgrow me.
But it hasn't exactly happened.
No one's stepped forward.
Well, maybe you
need to step down
to allow someone to step up.
(sighs) Jim Gordon.
Clean-shaven man of leisure.
(chuckles)
Ten years.
I wonder what Bruce
will think of Selina.
She's become quite
the it girl around town.
(beeping)
♪♪♪♪
(gasps)
(siren wailing in distance)
(indistinct chatter)
So they have no idea when
Nygma actually escaped?
He wasn't in his
cell this morning.
This is where the guard lives.
The one that didn't
show for work.
All right. I got it.
Stay here in case
something else comes in.
All right.
(car horns honking in distance)
GCPD.
No! Okay. Okay...
Shut up! Talk to him.
(grunting)
This is Detective Bullock.
(breath trembling)
You understand?
Oh, my God.
You understand
what you have to do?
Oh, my God.
I don't have a choice!
(gunshot) (body thuds)
(door opens)
What the hell happened, Harvey?
What did Harper say?
I want to hear it from you.
We, uh, tracked down
this Arkham guard
we thought maybe
helped Nygma escape.
I shot him.
End of story.
You're confessing...
to killing an unarmed
suspect in cold blood.
That's what happened.
You got to let it go.
Harvey, I don't
know if you think
you're protecting
yourself or someone else,
but you need to
change your story.
Otherwise you're
going to Blackgate.
And you know what
happens to cops in Blackgate.
That's what happened.
So let it go.
(indistinct chatter)
All right, first things first.
Whoever here doesn't believe
Harvey Bullock is innocent
can leave right now.
Good.
(sighs) You think
Nygma's behind this?
Maybe. But he's been
inside Arkham for ten years.
It's not like he suddenly
decided to break out.
He had help. ALVAREZ:
Penguin gets released today.
You think...?
Yeah. Put a tail on him.
In the meantime, I
want every other cop
in this city on the hunt
for Edward Nygma.
We looked into the dead guard.
He used to be associated
with a southside gang.
Got an address.
An old warehouse.
All right. You
and I will hit it.
Rest of you have
your orders. Let's go.
(rat squeaking)
(gasps)
(panting)
(echoing): Hello?!
Anybody?!
Anybody!
"Dear Ed, my old friend.
"Half of Gotham
thinks you a madman.
"The other half
has forgotten you.
It's time to remind
them who the Riddler is."
"I've given you all you
need. Follow the instructions.
Oswald."
(laughing)
Oswald...
what are you planning?
♪♪♪♪
(clamoring)
Mr. Cobblepot, what's the first
thing you'll do as a free man?
I will lay flowers on the
grave of my beloved mother.
And what of Jim Gordon's
role in your incarceration?
Will you seek revenge?
The best revenge
against Jim Gordon
will be a life spent
serving the city I love.
What do you say, young man?
How'd you like an exclusive?
- Yeah, sure.
- Yeah.
(reporters clamoring)
Your jacket and hat.
What?
Now!
(liquid dripping)
(echoing): GCPD!
GCPD.
HARPER: This is the place.
HARPER: Good God.
GORDON: Did your lead
say anything about this?
HARPER: About a
gangland bloodbath?
No.
What the hell is going on?
GORDON: Someone's
covering their tracks.
There was a break-in
in a government
warehouse last week.
Those crates have
U.S. Army markings.
(loud clatter)
Find the back stairs.
GCPD!
I know you're here.
Show yourself.
DISTORTED VOICE:
I am not your enemy.
Don't touch the bodies.
Don't move!
Grenade!
♪♪♪♪
HARPER: Okay, thanks.
(siren chirps outside)
Bomb squad said the
bodies were rigged with C-4.
Whoever that was
saved our lives.
Suggesting...
that he wasn't the
one that killed them.
Could be he's hunting the
same person we're hunting.
Whoever's really
behind all this.
- You thinking
he's on our side?
- Yeah, maybe.
That C-4 has to have been
what was stolen from the
government warehouse.
Which means most
of it's still missing.
Just got a call. Mayor
James vanished,
and our tail lost Penguin.
Sir, what the hell is going on?
First Nygma, now Penguin.
Keep it simple.
Imagine all that C-4.
What's the biggest target
in Gotham right now?
Double security
for tonight's event.
I have to talk to Bruce
Wayne and Alfred Pennyworth.
Hello, old friend.
- Oswald...
- One more word,
and I will put a bullet
in you here and now.
Drive.
(engine starts)
Oswald...
Don't talk!
Turn around!
Remember when
we stood here, Jim,
all those years ago?
Don Falcone wanted you
to shoot me. You refused.
Now don't you wish
you had done it?
Everyone will know you did this.
(laughs quietly)
Let them!
We both know that this
has been a long time coming.
Our story is...
over, old friend.
You want to kill me, fine.
But there's no need to
attack the Wayne gala.
What are you talking about?
Breaking Nygma out of Arkham.
The attacks on the gangs.
What do you think,
you're gonna be able
to destroy Wayne Tower
and no one's gonna notice?
I don't know what
you're talking about.
You and I stood
shoulder to shoulder
on those barricades,
ready to die for this city.
Six months later,
you locked me up like an animal!
This begins and ends
with you and me!
You're telling the truth.
Goodbye, Jim.
(cocks pistol) Turn around!
You know, you made a mistake
bringing me out to this pier.
Don't talk!
Or maybe you just
have a short memory.
(gasping)
(screaming)
♪♪ Blood-filled ♪♪
(indistinct chatter)
♪♪ Jewel of life ♪♪
So, this is Bruce's new Gotham.
I like the old one.
Selina?
How wonderful to see you again.
It's been far, far too long.
Where is he?
Well, I-I'm afraid travels
abroad haven't increased
Master Bruce's respect
for punctuality, Miss Kyle.
I came here to tell him
to stop spying on me.
I don't understand.
I was out the other night
and I felt someone watching me.
I know it was Bruce.
Oh, I see, right, well,
that makes perfect sense.
So you come here tonight
dressed to the nines to tell him
that you want nothing
more to do with him.
Is that the kind of gist of it?
He left, Alfred.
Everything we went through,
and one day he's just gone.
He doesn't get to come
back after ten years
and act like nothing's happened.
On this, we absolutely agree.
I do, however, feel
it might be something
that you want to
tell him yourself.
He needs to stay away.
♪♪ Diamond veins ♪♪
♪♪ Running through me... ♪♪
Nygma?
BARBARA: Well, look at you.
I think Bruce is gonna regret
being gone all these years.
Follow me.
(door opens)
(door closes)
NYGMA: Credit to Bruce.
He did not skimp
on the caterers.
Hungry?
(muffled): Uh-uh.
(chuckles) (TV
playing indistinctly)
Your loss.
Not long now.
NEWSWOMAN: Bruce Wayne's first
public appearance in nearly a decade.
(crowd applauding)
Lucius.
Lee.
Heard about Harvey...
How is he? How's Jim?
I don't know.
I was hoping he would be here.
Ah. (clears throat)
Ladies and gentlemen.
Uh, my name is Alfred
Thaddeus Crane Pennyworth.
And I'd very much
like to welcome you
on behalf of Wayne
Enterprises and Bruce Wayne
to the, uh, future... of Gotham.
(on TV): As you know,
ten years ago, the battle...
Oh, come on.
Where is that brat?
BARBARA: Hello, Ed.
Barbara Kean.
In red.
(chuckles)
Oh, no.
Please tell me you
are not here to stop me.
Barbara...
Do you even remember
how amazing you used to be?
Honey, I'm still amazing.
(chuckles) I just made a choice.
You made a choice.
Some of us don't
get to make choices.
I'm The Riddler.
And tonight Gotham
will remember that.
By blowing up this ding-dong?
Didn't you do that already?
It's a callback.
I was waiting for Bruce
to begin his speech.
You know, come
out, present a riddle.
Only Bruce doesn't
seem to want to show.
So I think I'm
gonna have to imp...
(muffled grunting)
(sighs)
BARBARA: Sorry, Ed.
Not tonight.
Wayne Enterprises
will devote itself
to making this future a reality.
(doors bang open)
- Lee.
- (Alfred continues indistinctly)
- THOMPKINS: Jim.
- I'm fine. Evacuate the building.
- Get these people
out of here.
- JAMES: Help!
Gordon!
Help! Gordon!
Gordon, help! (crowd screaming)
This lunatic.
He kidnapped me again.
He tried to blow me up. Again!
But we stopped him.
You're welcome.
Take care of the mayor, please.
Get that thing off of him.
Excuse me.
There were four crates of C-4.
Where are the rest?
That's all he gave me.
- He said Penguin broke him out.
- No.
It wasn't Penguin.
Get him out of there.
What?
Hey! Get off me.
Penguin not's just the patsy.
He's not even the real threat.
Which means there must be...
♪♪♪♪
(beeping)
GORDON: If this bomb goes off
and Wayne Tower falls,
it'll take out other buildings.
A lot of people are gonna die.
You all need to leave right now.
So you can stay? Absolutely not.
It's too late.
We'd never get far enough away.
Ms. Kean is right;
this stops right here.
So how do we defuse it?
We'd have to sever the
connectors to the detonator,
but the bomber
must have hidden it.
The wires go up
inside the model.
It must be in one
of the buildings.
I tracked down a gang today...
They had bomb-making materials,
pictures of buildings.
One in particular:
Gotham Clock Tower.
(alarm ringing)
Let's go.
In here.
(grunts)
Wait, wait, wait.
(beeping)
Wait. This particular
detonator has a gyroscope.
Which means someone will
have to hold it up and steady
while you detach
the wires from below.
I have doctor's
hands, I can do it.
Fine. Lucius.
LUCIUS: All right,
the trigger connection
should be different
than the others.
THOMPKINS: Okay,
I see two green wires.
I'm gonna cut this one.
♪♪♪♪
(beeping)
(sighs) (Barbara sighs)
- The other one. The other one.
- The other one.
- Yes, the other one.
(sighs)
Never doubted you for a minute.
Strange.
We designed a new clock
tower, but this is the old one.
That's the answer.
Who's behind all this, but...
but it's not possible.
HARPER: Sir.
Sir, Nygma's vanished.
There's more.
Mayor James ordered
Bullock sent to Blackgate.
He's about to be moved.
(sirens wailing in distance)
GORDON: Stop! Stop!
The person who framed you,
the one behind Nygma's breakout,
is it who I think it is?
Has he been faking it?
Jim, do not say his name!
Is it Jeremiah Valeska?
(grunts) Harvey.
Check him for a wire! What?
Under his shirt.
Check for a wire.
BULLOCK: Oh, God, it's too late.
He's miked.
Jim, you don't
know what he'll do.
I-I don't know about this.
How much is it again?
ORDERLY: Ten bucks is a
body punch. $20, you get the face.
Stabbing him is a C-note.
Huh.
(grunting)
Bad news, boss.
Our cover's blownskies.
(chuckles softly)
(cackles)
(gasps)
(car horns honking in distance)
(grunts)
OSWALD: Edward Nygma.
It is very good to see you.
Oswald... I thought
you weren't behind this.
I'm not.
But I thought you
might need some help,
and... what else
are friends for?
(chuckles)
You look well.
You, too.
A little thicker in the middle.
(chuckles)
Damn, it's good
to see you, Oswald.
(both chuckling)
(tires screeching)
Wh-What was that? What was that?
(screams)
(crash)
(horn honking)
What the hell was that?!
(coughs)
(whooshing)
(both screaming)
(sirens wailing in distance)
Alfred, when Bruce came
to me the day he got back
and told me what he was
planning, I didn't hesitate.
I believe in what he's doing,
but he's going to
need some help.
Has he thought
about telling Gordon?
Lucius, my old friend,
whoever Bruce decides to
take on this journey with him,
it's his decision.
Our role... is to serve.
(Oswald and Nygma straining)
Down!
- Get me down!
- Aah!
Something happened
tonight, didn't it?
Why won't you tell me?
Because everything
worked out okay, didn't it?
So why are we at your old club?
Because Mommy just
needs to get something.
♪♪ I ♪♪
♪♪ Now, I don't hardly... ♪♪
Wait here, okay?
♪♪ But I think I
could love her ♪♪
Turn around.
♪♪ Crimson and clover ♪♪
I won't ask again.
Surprise.
(grunting)
Easy.
It's just a surprise party.
For you, Barbara Kean,
queen of Gotham,
business titan. How exciting.
But there was another you, I...
I seem to recall.
Wasn't there?
Then again, there was, uh,
another me, too.
Oh, so hard holding
on to what's real. It's...
(grunts) It's enough
to drive you mad.
(chuckles)
(grunting)
No!
BARBARA LEE (screams): Mom!
Cute.
(panting)
She has your eyes.
For now.
No, put me down.
(whimpers) I...
think she...
nicked me, Daddy.
I...
Oh, boy.
Oh, dear me.
My sweet Ecco,
no longer my echo.
There will never
be one like you.
Really?
(chuckles)
But I suppose there
are other fish in the sea.
Let me...
down. (panting)
- Mom!
- Hush,
little Barbaras,
don't say a word.
Now we're going to play a...
little game. (panting)
By now, James Gordon
should have made it
to your apartment.
When he gets here,
I want you to deliver
a message. Okay?
(exhales, sniffles)
Okay?
(giggles)
(door opens)
GORDON: Barbara.
I'll call an ambulance.
Barbara.
He took her!
That lunatic took her!
He said you have to
come, and if you don't come,
he's gonna kill her.
Where?
The place where
he was born again.
He means Ace Chemicals.
You promise me.
I'll bring her back.
(door opens)
(door closes)
JEREMIAH: Come
along, Commissioner.
We're waiting.
The party's raging,
but it's well past the
princess's bedtime.
It's funny, being back here.
I can still feel my flesh
sizzle as it melted away.
Burns even now.
Ooh. Oh.
(screams)
I'm here.
Everything's gonna be fine.
You think so?
Personally, I'd say things
are about as far away from fine
as they could possibly
be, Barbara Lee.
What do I know? I did
just spend the last ten years
in the funny farm. (giggles)
What do you want, Jeremiah?
Is there a Jeremiah here?
So what do I call you?
Uh...
I don't know.
Call me... Jack.
Mm, no, no, no,
that's not right.
J-Joseph. John. Jay.
I-I don't know. I just...
I feel something new crawling
from the primordial
ooze that was me.
Something...
beautiful.
How long have you been
pretending to be brain-dead?
How long have you
been pretending?
That's a joke. I know
you're not pretending.
That's far enough, James.
(clucks)
GORDON: But you
still haven't told me.
Why?
Why keep pretending?
I was waiting for
him to come home.
We're bound together, he and I.
It's the one thing I knew
for certain, the one thing
I knew was true.
And then he just...
abandoned us.
Do you know how it
feels to have the one,
the only thing you love
ripped away from you?
It feels like this.
- No!
- (screams)
(laughs)
- (grunts)
- (shouts)
(laughs)
Disappointing as tonight was,
I will say, it is fun carving up
Filet-O-Commissioner. (giggling)
(clang)
Who's there?!
What do you want?!
Show yourself!
(whooshing)
You.
(Jeremiah laughing)
(laughing)
♪♪♪♪
It's okay. It's all right.
I got you, okay?
So, he comes out of nowhere,
saves you and Barbara Lee,
and just disappears?
Yeah.
So, the dude's on our side?
I think so.
Hey, this old thing.
I thought we, uh, mothballed
this after reunification.
I had 'em dig it out
for old times' sake.
I sent a note to Wayne Manor.
I thought Bruce might want
to be here when we light it.
Good evening, gentlemen.
Master Bruce sends
his profound apologies.
He's otherwise engaged.
He's been busy a lot
since he came back.
Yes, indeed.
And I hear that you're retiring.
I may stick around
a while yet.
♪♪♪♪
You're there, aren't you?
Do you have any
idea what you did...
just leaving?
You were all I had.
And I know you
wanted to protect me.
But I didn't want
to be protected.
I wanted you.
Say something.
(quietly): Say something.
There was no other way, Selina.
I had to go.
So what happens now?
I don't know.
But I'll never leave
Gotham again.
Return the diamond.
(whooshing)
Like hell.
"Gotham is mine."
That's what he said.
I was there, Oswald.
I did not spend ten
years in Blackgate
to give my city to a
man dressed like a bat!
Yes!
(grunts) Go!
We have to find out who he is
and show him
that this is our city!
Agreed.
(gasps)
Tomorrow?
Tomorrow.
Yet in the darkness,
there will be light.
That's what you
promised Master Bruce
all those years
ago in the alley.
You saved him.
Gave him hope.
Holy Mother.
♪♪♪♪
Who is he?
A friend.
♪♪♪♪